<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-08T13:06:22+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">WBarton</title><subtitle>Will Barton: Nottinghamshire based full-stack developer, specialising in JavaScript development and accessible user interfaces.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A New Blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/new-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A New Blog" /><published>2015-03-18T17:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-18T17:50:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/new-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/new-blog">&lt;p&gt;I have decided to start over and move to using Jekyll to mange this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the obligatory first post, but I am going to retro fit some of my old post from my MA reflective journal into this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try and keep this fresh and resurrect the old twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">I have decided to start over and move to using Jekyll to mange this site.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pillow OSX error</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/pillow-osx-error" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pillow OSX error" /><published>2015-03-18T17:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-18T17:50:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/pillow-osx-error</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/pillow-osx-error">&lt;p&gt;Got an error installing pillow on OS X, error below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;clang -fno-strict-aliasing -fno-common -dynamic -I/usr/local/include -I/usr/local/opt/sqlite/include -DNDEBUG -g -fwrapv -O3 -Wall -Wstrict-prototypes -I/System/Library/Frameworks/Tcl.framew
ork/Headers -I/System/Library/Frameworks/Tk.framework/Headers -I/usr/X11/include/freetype2 -IlibImaging -I/usr/X11/include -I/usr/local/include -I/Users/wbarton/code/.virtualenvs/ketchup-pin
knwhites/include -I/usr/include -I/usr/local/Cellar/python/2.7.8_2/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/2.7/include/python2.7 -c _imagingft.c -o build/temp.macosx-10.9-x86_64-2.7/_imagingft.

_imagingft.c:62:10: fatal error: 'freetype/fterrors.h' file not found

#include &amp;lt;freetype/fterrors.h&amp;gt;

         ^

1 error generated.

error: command 'clang' failed with exit status 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed by symlinking freetype to freetype2 by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ln -s /usr/local/include/freetype2 /usr/local/include/freetype
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="python" /><category term="error" /><category term="notes" /><summary type="html">Got an error installing pillow on OS X, error below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Graceful Degradation vs. Progressive Enhancement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/graceful-degradation-vs-progressive-enhancement" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Graceful Degradation vs. Progressive Enhancement" /><published>2012-07-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-07-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/graceful-degradation-vs-progressive-enhancement</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/graceful-degradation-vs-progressive-enhancement">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to responsive web design and at which end of the design you should choose it is between Graceful Degradation and Progressive Enhancement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasoning behind Graceful Degradation is that the design should function on as many possible browsers and devices using the latest technologies but still catering for users whose systems may not support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progressive Enhancement is the opposite the first step is the minimal design and then the design can be gradually “enhanced”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All websites should follow Graceful Degradation to some degree, not relying on Javascript effects, using pseudo elements like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;:before&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;:after&lt;/code&gt; to insert important information and using new techniques like box and text shadows and rounded corners (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;border-radius&lt;/code&gt;) as an enhancement instead of the be all and end all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… Responsive web design should start with mobile.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When it comes to responsive web design and at which end of the design you should choose it is between Graceful Degradation and Progressive Enhancement</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Responsive Web Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/why-responsive-web-design" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Responsive Web Design" /><published>2012-06-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-06-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/why-responsive-web-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/why-responsive-web-design">&lt;p&gt;In a blog post titled “Responsive design — harnessing the power of media queries” Google address responsive web design its growing popularity and how in recent years they have found an increase in traffic from mobile devices to many sites. They consider theses nuber to be significant an have set out to cater for this group of browsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They mention the choice between creating a mobile specific website, or modifing current ‘full’ websites and new websites to be optimised and render in bothe mobile and non-mobile browsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other reasons behind responsive web design other than aesthetic Breheny  &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2012) states “maintaining a single shared site preserves a canonical URL, avoiding any complicated redirects, and simplifies the sharing of web addresses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blog post continues with a discussion about how they could fulfill the following self set guidelines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our pages should render legibly at any screen resolution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We mark up one set of content, making it viewable on any device&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should never show a horizontal scrollbar, whatever the window size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here the blog post because a tutorial about how to implement different techniques like media queries and fluid images, but the important point to take away from the article is that google are using responsive web design because they consider it the future of web design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article: &lt;a href=&quot;http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.co.uk/2012/04/responsive-design-harnessing-power-of.html&quot;&gt;http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.co.uk/2012/04/responsive-design-harnessing-power-of.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breheny, R., Jung, E., Zürrer, M. (2012) &lt;em&gt;Official Google Webmaster Central Blog: Responsive design – harnessing the power of media queries&lt;/em&gt;. [online] Available at: http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.co.uk/2012/04/responsive-design-harnessing-power-of.html [Accessed: 26 May 2012].&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In a blog post titled “Responsive design — harnessing the power of media queries” Google address responsive web design its growing popularity and how in recent years they have found an increase in traffic from mobile devices to many sites. They consider theses nuber to be significant an have set out to cater for this group of browsers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bottom up</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/bottom-up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bottom up" /><published>2012-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/bottom-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/bottom-up">&lt;p&gt;What I have often found is that I am designing a full screen website and then once complete designing every break point down to a mobile website and then in the CSS allowing for bottom-up design when in fact according to Jeffery Zeldman what I should be doing is starting from the bottom and working up designing the website for mobile without thinking about the final design for desktop computers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What I have often found is that I am designing a full screen website and then once complete designing every break point down to a mobile website and then in the CSS allowing for bottom-up design when in fact according to Jeffery Zeldman what I should be doing is starting from the bottom and working up designing the website for mobile without thinking about the final design for desktop computers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Designer and the Grid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/the-designer-and-the-grid" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Designer and the Grid" /><published>2012-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/the-designer-and-the-grid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/the-designer-and-the-grid">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Designer and the Grid&lt;/em&gt; by Lucienne Roberts and Julia Thrift begins with a history of grid layout and places its conception in about 1450 following the introduction of printing from moveable type in Europe. Grids were born from necessity, pages needed structure and multiple pages needed consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roberts and Thrift explain that the grid can be considered a foundation for great design or a noose inhibiting creativity. I agree with both comments but only the former in more recent years when I have designed websites as a professional in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book applies the concept of the grid to a wider context like music and architecture, an interesting idea and it does flow nicely into digital design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roberts, L. and Thrift, J. (2002) &lt;em&gt;The Designer and the Grid&lt;/em&gt;. Sussex: RotoVision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Designer and the Grid by Lucienne Roberts and Julia Thrift begins with a history of grid layout and places its conception in about 1450 following the introduction of printing from moveable type in Europe. Grids were born from necessity, pages needed structure and multiple pages needed consistency.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Maintenance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/maintenance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maintenance" /><published>2012-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/maintenance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/maintenance">&lt;p&gt;The problem with mobile specific websites is that they often display duplicate content, responsive web design helps to solve that problem by creating a website that works for all devices. Long term this mean less maintenance because there is only one web site instead of two, also URLs are not different which can allow for better sharing capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apps are still relevant and will continue to be, except they are becoming less native; utilising modern web development techniques.&lt;br /&gt;
In an interview forThe linkeIn app is created with HTML5 and node.js and. Claims they claim that only 5% is Is native.&lt;br /&gt;
In an article on Venture Beats written by Jolie O’Dell that contains snippets from an interview with Kiran Prasad the head of the development team at LinkedIn said “You can’t take a mobile app and just scale it up to tablet or desktop,” Which is true an app gives a better mobile experience. He continues by saying “A lot of responsive design is building one site that works everywhere, and that works for websites. But it’s bad for apps… You have to come up with a completely different design because of the use case.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apps will not disappear but responsive website have become more app-like in their appearance when viewed on mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The problem with mobile specific websites is that they often display duplicate content, responsive web design helps to solve that problem by creating a website that works for all devices. Long term this mean less maintenance because there is only one web site instead of two, also URLs are not different which can allow for better sharing capabilities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bottom Up</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/bottoms-up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bottom Up" /><published>2012-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/bottoms-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/bottoms-up">&lt;p&gt;CSS renders from top to bottom hence &lt;em&gt;cascading&lt;/em&gt; style sheet. The style sheet is referenced at the start of the markup in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;head&lt;/code&gt;. The reason for this is the sooner it is referenced the sooner the browser can begin to render the website. This stops the flash of unstyled content (FOUC), a problem more commonly associated with a slower Internet connection. Like mobile data connections?&lt;br /&gt;
There is another exploit of CSS that can benefit the mobile user, &lt;em&gt;start small&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Declare the styles for mobile browsers at the start of the CSS, this stops the browser reading and rendering the full site before the mobile site. Then using media queries to build on the design and optimise it for larger screens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">CSS renders from top to bottom hence cascading style sheet. The style sheet is referenced at the start of the markup in the head. The reason for this is the sooner it is referenced the sooner the browser can begin to render the website. This stops the flash of unstyled content (FOUC), a problem more commonly associated with a slower Internet connection. Like mobile data connections? There is another exploit of CSS that can benefit the mobile user, start small. Declare the styles for mobile browsers at the start of the CSS, this stops the browser reading and rendering the full site before the mobile site. Then using media queries to build on the design and optimise it for larger screens.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grids: A change of thought</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/grids-a-change-of-thought" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grids: A change of thought" /><published>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/grids-a-change-of-thought</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/grids-a-change-of-thought">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For some graphic designers, it has become an unquestioned part of the working process that yield precision, order, and clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For others it is symbolic of Old Guard aesthetic oppression, a stifling cage that hinders the search for expression.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;Timothy Samara in &lt;cite title=&quot;Making and Breaking the Grid&quot;&gt;Making and Breaking the Grid&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my reading week(s) continue I came across this fantastic quote in “Making and Breaking the Grid” written by Timothy Samara.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been reading books about traditional layout design, a topic that can inform my research into design for the mobile web. I have often avoided grids because the strict proportions that can inhibit some types of design, but I have found since graduating from my undergraduate degree and working in a quick paced industry that grids can streamline the design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a tried and tested grid as a foundation for a website can ultimately lead to a better and more robust design. A grid is a list of rules to follow to create an aesthetic yet functional design.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For some graphic designers, it has become an unquestioned part of the working process that yield precision, order, and clarity. For others it is symbolic of Old Guard aesthetic oppression, a stifling cage that hinders the search for expression. Timothy Samara in Making and Breaking the Grid</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/reading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading&amp;#8230;" /><published>2012-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/reading">&lt;p&gt;For the next couple of days/week I have decided to apply my attentions to reading. My chosen area? Traditional layout design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top three books I am currently working my way through are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Layout Book&lt;/em&gt; — Gavin Ambrose and Paul Harris, 2007&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making and Breaking the Grid&lt;/em&gt; — Timothy Samara, 2002&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Designer and the Grid&lt;/em&gt; — Lucienne Robert and Julia Thrift, 2002&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three book are very detailed and between them cover most of the topic that I wanted to research. I want to supplement the findings from my research with some deconstructions of current design, especially web sites that claim to use and not to use grids.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For the next couple of days/week I have decided to apply my attentions to reading. My chosen area? Traditional layout design.</summary></entry></feed>